Michael B. James, Ph.D.

■ hello@michaelbjames.com | ↑ michaelbjames.com | ↑ michaelbjames | ↑ michael-b-james

Research Mission

Building the next generation of Human-AI programming environments requires a deep understanding both of how AI-assistants operate and of how programmers use them. My work spans both, through my experience with AI-agents, Programming Languages techniques, and Human-Computer Interactions methodologies. I identify developer-centric challenges and overcome them with a novel combination of stochastic and formal techniques.

Education -

University of California, San Diego

- · Ph.D., Computer Science 2018-2024
- · M.S. Computer Science 2021

Advisor: Nadia Polikarpova

Tufts University

· B.S. Computer Science 2015

Publications

- [THESIS]: **Exploratory Phenomena in Program Synthesis.** *Michael B. James.* 2024.
 - [LEAP]: **Validating AI-Generated Code with Live Programming**. Kasra Ferdowsi*, Ruanqianqian (Lisa) Huang*, *Michael B. James*, Nadia Polikarpova, Sorin Lerner. *CHI*. May 2024.
 - [GCP]: **Grounded Copilot: How Programmers Interact with Code-Generating Models**. Shraddha Barke*, *Michael B. James**, Nadia Polikarpova. *OOPSLA*. October 2023. *Distinguished Paper Award*
 - [PRS]: **Program Recognition in Synthesis**. *Michael B. James*, Nadia Polikarpova. *PLATEAU*. November 2021.
 - [H+]: **Digging for Fold: Synthesis-aided API Discovery for Haskell**. *Michael B. James*, Zheng Guo, Ziteng Wang, Shivani Dosh, Hila Peleg, Ranjit Jhala, Nadia Polikarpova. *OOPSLA*. November 2020.
- [TYGAR]: **Program Synthesis by Type-Guided Abstraction Refinement**. Zheng Guo, *Michael B. James*, David Justo, Jiaxiao Zhou, Ziteng Wang, Ranjit Jhala, Nadia Polikarpova *47th ACM SIGPLAN Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages* (POPL 2020). January 2020.

Work Experience

Founding AI/UX Research Scientist. Sailplane PBC. New York City. Jul 2024 - current

- · Second hire at venture-backed AI startup empowering developers with human-AI collaborative programming
- · Responsible for key differentiating features in our highly-parallel agent
- · Designed and built several AI agents, testing various product ideas with user-collaboration as a core principle
- · Evaluated our alpha against different public agents, following the latest research methods
- · Stepped in where needed: delivered cross-cutting features needed to secure \$5M in seed round funding

Research Intern. Microsoft. Remote. Summer 2022

Mentors: Arjun Radhakrishna, Gustavo Soares

- · Worked with the PROSE team on novel interactive program synthesis tool for API migrations.
- · Gathered changing product goals from several internal customers in concrete action plan

Software Engineer II. Jana Mobile. Boston, Massachusetts. Feb 2017 - Jun 2018

- · Redesigned revenue reporting pipeline for live business metrics
- · Designed & implemented user profile data collection, from Cassandra DB to Android+Chromium frontend
- · Productionized data scientist analyses for metrics and alert generation on business status
- · Managed data scientists' APIs for product metrics, including Kafka pipelines

Software Engineer I. Uber Technologies. San Francisco. Jul 2015 - Dec 2016

- · Owned business.uber.com. Led service migration to React.
- · Lead team migration to golang, with a new anti-fraud microservice.
- · Managed and contributed to 12 microservices.

Research Projects

Human-AI Collaborative Programming 2021-2024

Our groundbreaking study identified how programmers use Copilot: they either *accelerate* through a task, or use the tool to *explore* their problem space^[GCP]. Our findings identified difficulty in validating Al-generated code, but our technique with live programming eases this difficulty^[LEAP]. Current work-inprogress highlights the "wisdom of the crowds" of an LLM to assist in design space exploration.

Type Directed Synthesis in Haskell 2018-2021

Our novel synthesis technique generates Haskell programs that are guaranteed to satisfy the user's intent quickly by using abstract refinements^[TYGAR]. A user-study proves that our multi-modal search with examples and tests aids program comprehension, allowing a user to complete more tasks^[H+]. A followup study reinforces the need for tool-assisted code validation^[PRS].

Talks

Grounded Copilot: How Programmers Interact with Code-Generating Models. 2023 - OOPSLA (Cascais, Portugal)

Program Recognition in Synthesis. 2021 - PLATEAU (Carnegie Mellon University)

Digging for Fold: Synthesis-aided API Discovery for Haskell. 2021 - OOPSLA (Chicago), 2020 - OOPSLA 2020 (virtual)

Component-based Type Driven Synthesis. 2019 - University of California, San Diego

Teaching -

Graduate Teaching Assistant (UC San Diego)

Courses: undergraduate and graduate programming

languages.

Fall 2023, Spring 2022, Spring 2021, Fall 2019.

Supervisor: Nadia Polikarpova

Undergraduate Teaching Assistant (Tufts University)

Course: undergraduate programming languages

Fall 2014.

Supervisor: Kathleen Fisher

Service

Reviewer: CHI 2024, PLATEAU 2024

Student Volunteer Co-Chair: PLDI 2023, 2024 Artifact Evaluation: ICFP 2020, ICFP 2021

Skills-

Python, Typescript, Haskell, Elixir, Program Synthesis, Artificial Intelligence, AI Agents, Distributed Systems, User Research, Quantitative Research, Qualitative Research, Evaluation, Data Science, Compilers, Type Systems, Web development, git, jira, react